<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Englands absolute monarchy, or government of Great Britaine. Composed out of these three kindes, monarchy, aristrocracie [sic] and democracie. From whence the kingdome of England derives a fit parallell, by a King, a House of Peers, and a House of Commons. From whence is collected and explained the prerogative of the King, the authority of the Peers, and the priviledge of the Commons. Whereunto is annexed His Majesties resolution to maintaine the priviledges of the Commons, and the full authority of the Protestant religion.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1642</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 9 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 5 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A83945</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing E2937</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E107_3</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R18866</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99860482</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99860482</idno>
            <idno type="VID">112602</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A83945)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 112602)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 19:E107[3])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Englands absolute monarchy, or government of Great Britaine. Composed out of these three kindes, monarchy, aristrocracie [sic] and democracie. From whence the kingdome of England derives a fit parallell, by a King, a House of Peers, and a House of Commons. From whence is collected and explained the prerogative of the King, the authority of the Peers, and the priviledge of the Commons. Whereunto is annexed His Majesties resolution to maintaine the priviledges of the Commons, and the full authority of the Protestant religion.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Thomas Bankes,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1642.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Signatures: A⁴.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Charles --  I, --  King of England, 1600-1649.</term>
               <term>Prerogative, Royal --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  Politics and government --  1642-1649 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-07</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>Geremy Carnes</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>Geremy Carnes</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:112602:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:112602:1"/>
            <p>ENGLANDS Abſolute MONARCHY, Or Government of GREAT BRITAINE.</p>
            <p>Compoſed out of theſe three kindes, <hi>Monarchy, Ariſtrocracie</hi> and <hi>Democracie.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>From whence the Kingdome of <hi>England</hi> derives a fit parallell, by a <hi>King,</hi> a <hi>Houſe</hi> of <hi>Peers,</hi> and a <hi>Houſe</hi> of <hi>Commons.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>From whence is collected and explained the Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogative of the <hi>King,</hi> the Authority of the <hi>Peers,</hi> and the Priviledge of the <hi>Commons.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Whereunto is annexed His Majeſties Reſolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to maintaine the Priviledges of the Commons, and the full Authority of the Proteſtant RELIGION.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed for <hi>Thomas Bankes,</hi> 1642.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:112602:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:112602:2"/>
            <head>
               <hi>Englands</hi> abſolute <hi>Monarchy,</hi> or <hi>Government</hi> of <hi>Great Britain.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Here are three kindes of Government amongſt men, <hi>Abſolute Monarchy, Ariſtocracie</hi> and <hi>Democracie,</hi> and all of theſe having particular conveni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences, and inconveniences, the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience and wiſdome of our An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſtors hat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſo moulded this out of a mixture of theſe as to give to this Kingdome (as farre as hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane prudence can provide) the conveniences of all three, without the inconveniences of any one, as long as the ballance hangs eeven betweene the three eſtates, and they runne jointly on in their pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per channell (begetting verdure and fertillity in the medowes of either on both ſides) and the overflow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of either on either ſide raiſe no deluge or in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>undation.</p>
            <p>The ill of abſolute Monarchy is <hi>Tyranny.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The ill of Ariſtocracie is Faction and Diviſion.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:112602:3"/>
            <p>The ills of Democracie are <hi>Tumults, Violence, and Licentiouſneſſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The good of Monarchy <hi>is the uniting of a Nation under one head to reſiſt invaſion from abroad, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection at home.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The good of Ariſtocracie <hi>is the conjunction of Councell in the ableſt perſons of a State, for the publicke benefit.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The good of Democracie <hi>is liberty and the cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage and induſtry which liberty begets.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In this Kingdome the Lawes are jointly made by a <hi>King,</hi> by a Houſe of <hi>Peeres,</hi> and by a Houſe of <hi>Commons,</hi> choſen by the people, all having free Votes, and particular priviledges.</p>
            <p>The government according to the Lawes is tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted to the King, power of treaties of Warre and Peace, of making Peers, of chuſing Officers and Councellors for State. Judges for Law, Comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders for Forts and Caſtles, giving Com<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ſſions for raiſing men to make warre abroad, or to prevent or provide againſt invaſions, or inſurrections at home, benefit of confiſcations, power of pardoning, and ſome more of the like kinde, are placed in the King. And this kinde of regulated Monarchy having this power to preſerve that authority, which without it would be diſabled to preſerve Laws in their force, and the Subjects in their liberties and proprieties, is intended to draw to him ſuch a reſpect and relation from the great ones, as may hinder the ills of Divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion and Faction, and ſuch a feare and reverence
<pb facs="tcp:112602:3"/> from the people as may hinder Tumults, Violence and licentiouſneſſe.</p>
            <p>Againe, that the Prince may not make uſe of this high and perpetuall power to the hurt of thoſe for whoſe good he hath it, and make uſe of publick ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity for the gaine of his private favourites and followers, to the detriment of his people, the Houſe of Commons, an excellent conſerver of liberty, but never intended for any ſhare in government, or the chuſing of them that ſhould govern, is ſolely intru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted with the firſt propoſitions concerning the le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vies of moneys (which is the ſinewes as wel of peace as warre) and the impeaching of thoſe, who for their owne ends, though countenanced by any ſurrepti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiouſly gotten command of the King, have violated that Law, which he is bound (when he knowes it) to protect, and to the protection of which they were bound to adviſe him, at leaſt not to ſerve him in the contrary.</p>
            <p>And the Lords being tr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſted with a judicatory power, ate an excellent s<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>eene and banke betweene the Prince and People, to aſſiſt each againſt any in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>croachments of the other, and by juſt judgements to preſerve that Law which ought to be the rule of every one of the three.</p>
            <p>This is the exact forme of government eſtabli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed in the Kingdome of England, which I have publiſhed for the ſatisfaction of all thoſe that deſire to be informed of the manner and ground of the go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ent of this State.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:112602:4"/>
            <p>It being neceſſary in theſe troubleſome times that all men ſhould know how to obey both King and Parliament, how to maintaine the Kings juſt and royall Prerogative, and likewiſe how to defend the juſt priviledges of Parliament.</p>
            <p>For as the three kindes of Government are in a friendly combination united and become one abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute government, ſo the Kings royall Authority, the judicatory power of the Lords, and the juſt pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viledge of the Commons, are firmely united to make one abſolute power.</p>
            <p>Which intimates unto us, that to maintaine one onely, is not our duty, or two, and neglect the third, but to maintaine a firme and inſeparable union: for to make a diviſion is the firſt ſtep to diſſolution: wee ought not to maintaine the Kings regall Preroga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive, to ſuppreſſe the judicatory power of the Lords, nor the judicatory power of the Lords to make breach of the priviledges of the Commons, but maintaine each in its proper degree, by that meanes to make up an abſolute <hi>Monarchy.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb facs="tcp:112602:4"/>
            <head>His Majeſties Letter to both Hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes of PARLIAMENT.</head>
            <p>HIS Majeſty perceiving the manifold diſtr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions which now are in this Kingdome, which cannot but bring great inconvenience, and miſchiefe to this whole Government; In which, as his Majeſty is moſt chiefly intereſſed, ſo he holds himſelfe by many Reaſons moſt obliged to do what in him lies, for the preventing thereof; though he might juſtly expect (as moſt proper for the duty of Subjects) that Propoſitions for the remedies of theſe Evils, ought rather to come to him, then from him; yet his Fatherly care of all his people being ſuch, That hee will rather lay by any particular reſpect of his owne dignity, then that any time ſhould be loſt, for prevention of theſe threatning Evils, which can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not admit the delayes of the ordinary proceedings in Parliament; Doth thinke it fit to make theſe enſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing propoſitions to both Houſes of Parliament.</p>
            <p>That they will with all ſpeed full into a ſerious conſideration of all thoſe particulars, which they ſhall hold neceſſary, as well for the upholding and maintaining of his Majeſties juſt and Regall Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity,
<pb facs="tcp:112602:5"/> and for the ſetling of his Revenue; As for the preſent and future eſtabliſhing of their priviledges, the free and quiet enjoying of their Eſtates and For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunes, the liberties of their perſons, the ſecurity of the true Religion now profeſſed in the Church of England, and the ſetling of Ceremonies in ſuch a manner, as may take away all juſt offence: Which when they ſhall have digeſted, and compoſed into one entire body, that ſo his Majeſty and themſelves may bee able to make the more cleare judgement of them: It ſhall then appeare by what his Majeſty ſhall doe, how farre he hath been from intending or deſigning any of thoſe things, which the too great feares and jealouſies of ſome perſons ſeem to appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hend: And how ready he will be to equall and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed the greateſt examples of the moſt indulgent Princes in their Acts of Grace and Favour to their people.</p>
            <p>So that if all theſe preſent diſtractions (which ſo apparantly threaten the ruine of this Kingdome) do not (by the bleſſing of Almighty God) end in an happy and bleſſed Accomodation, his Majeſty will then be ready to call Heaven and Earth, God and Man to witneſſe, that it hath not failed on his part.</p>
         </div>
         <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
